<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way of peace, or, A discourse of the dangerous principles and practices of some pretended Protestants ... being certain brief ... writings of several learned Protestant authors : with divers additions perswasive to peace / by the author, a Protestant of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Protestant of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9234</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12197688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12197688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65328)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 905:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way of peace, or, A discourse of the dangerous principles and practices of some pretended Protestants ... being certain brief ... writings of several learned Protestant authors : with divers additions perswasive to peace / by the author, a Protestant of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Protestant of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56020:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Way of Peace:</hi> OR, A DISCOURSE OF THE <hi>Dangerous Principles and Practices</hi> OF SOME PRETENDED PROTESTANTS Tendered to the Conſideration of all ſober and ingenious Perſons.</p>
            <p>BEING Certain Brief Collections</p>
            <p>Out of the late Writings of ſeveral Learned Proteſtant Authors. With divers Additions perſwaſive to PEACE.</p>
            <p>By the Author, a Proteſtant of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nec mendacii utilitas eſt diuturna, nec veritatis damnum diu nocet.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the Weſt End of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:56020:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56020:2"/>
            <head>A Letter of the Authors to a Gentleman in <hi>London,</hi> upon occaſion of his ſending unto him the following Diſcourſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE ardent affections I bear to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Prince, and Country, have importuned me in order to Publick Peace, to preſent the incloſed Papers to your judicious view, hoping your Candor and Ingenuity will ſo far prevail with you, as not to reject this bold addreſs from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known hand. I leave them freely to your peruſal, and correction alſo; and if you cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them as it is ſaid <hi>Philoxenus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> did the Book that was ſent him to amend, with one great great blot from the beginning to the end, I ſhall not be offended with you, for probably they may deſerve it. But if you ſhall think them, or any part of them, may be uſeful for the publick good, to commit them to the Preſs; or if not, to the Fire. I ſee or hear of daily what mean and unworthy, yea, ſeditious and wicked Pamphlets come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb facs="tcp:56020:3"/>to abuſe the Government, to corrupt and debauch the Nation, and increaſe thoſe flames, we ought all ſtudiouſly to indeavour to quench. I hope if mine ſhall happen to ſee the light, although very mean and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, Country-like, will not be hurtful to any, and will give offence to none, but ſuch as are certainly bad. I hope I may with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty ſay thus much of the main ſubſtance and matter of the Diſcourſe; If it were (as it is nothing but ſolid Truth) impreſſed upon all our hearts in this Nation, it would certainly not only make his Sacred Majeſties Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more eaſie and portable to him, but this Church and Nation happy. I hope Sir you will pardon.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi>
                  <date>the 4th. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your very humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56020:3"/>
            <head>The way of PEACE: OR, A DISCOURSE OF THE Dangerous Principles and Practices OF SOME <hi>Pretended Proteſtants,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THere is nothing caſts ſo indeleble a blemiſh upon Religion <hi>(as a late worthy Author hath it)</hi> as when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it are turbulent, imperſuadable, ungovernable; when that which ſhould ſtrengthen the hands of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhall weaken them; when that which ſhould eaſe his care, and ſave the labour of his animadverſions, ſhall it ſelf awaken and raiſe his jealouſie; when that which ſhould enact his Laws in the very Conſciences of men, ſhall pretend to abrogate or diſpenſe with them; when men ſhall ſmite the two Tables one againſt the other,<note place="margin">An inquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cauſe of the preſent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 1674.</note> and put other limitations and conditions upon Princes than God hath — <hi>Whereſoever this is done,</hi> That Prince or Magiſtrate need be a very devout man indeed, that caſts a benigne aſpect upon that profeſſion which hath ſo malignant an influence upon his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And all conſidering men will with great reaſon doubt, whether that Religion be of God, that gives ſuch trouble to his Vicegerent, and whether that will carry men to Heaven hereafter, that makes Tumults, Confuſions, and a Hell upon Earth.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56020:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The more raiſed and elevated any Religion pretends to be, the more it profeſſeth a contempt of the World, the more it ſpeaks of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Contentation, Humility, and the more it glories in the hopes of another world, ſtill the more horribly abſurd, and contradictious will it be, that they that profeſs it, ſhould give countenance to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and diſturbance of Government,</hi> Tertullian gives ample teſtimony, <hi>Apol.</hi> c. 37. <hi>We want</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neither numbers nor Leaders, nor ſpirit to enable us for any attempt, but that we have learned to ſuffer ill, and not to do it; to obey and ſubmit, not to contend with our Rulers. And</hi> Ammianus Marcellinus <hi>a Pagan Soldier in</hi> Julians <hi>Army, gives this ſhort deſcription of the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aut hoc non eſt evangelium, aut no, non ſumus Chriſtiani.</note> Nil niſi juſtum ſuader &amp; lene. <hi>Its faith is compounded of nothing but mildneſs and innocency; it makes men juſt and honeſt; it fills mens hearts with vertuous principles</hi> — <hi>it teacheth men not to be troublers of the world, but to go quietly and inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively through it, with as little noiſe and provocation as is poſſible, and ſo to arrive at eternal reſt and peace in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as this is the known glory of Chriſtianity in general, ſo it was peculiarly of the Engliſh Reformation; it was eſtabliſhed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly by Law, and did not force its way by popular Tumult</hi> — <hi>and its pity it's glory afterwards ſhould be ſtained by the inſolence and impatience of thoſe that pretend to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's a great blot in the Writings of Mr.</hi> Calvin, <hi>that after he had diſcourſed rarely well of the power of Princes, and the duty of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, he undoes all again with an unhappy exception in theſe words,</hi> De privatis hominibus ſemper loquor, <hi>a paſſage of that ill aſpect upon Government, that it is ſuſpected by ſome. and not altogether without cauſe, that moſt of the Confuſions of Kingdoms which have happened ſince, and eſpecially the troubles of theſe Nations, have received encouragement, if not taken riſe from thence: But whether that be ſo or no, it is certain that it hath furniſht the Papiſts with a recrimination upon the Proteſtant Doctrine.</hi> — <hi>If it can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt us that our Churches are always infeſted with divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and the States under which we live, imbroiled in troubles, we have reaſon to be concerned; for it cannot be, but either the ſeed muſt be very bad that brings forth ſuch fruits, or the ſoyl very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt that makes good ſeed ſo degenerate; and whetherſoever of theſe two things be concluded on (as it is certain one muſt, and both may) we ill conſult, either for our ſelves or our profeſſion, that by our Diviſions, Diſputes, Turbuleneies, and Diſobediences, make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56020:4"/>the aforeſaid Dilemma inevitable. And all the wit and courage we ſhew in defending our private opinions, and maintaining our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parties, when the common cauſe and intereſt is by this means rendered odious and contemptible, is but like the fooliſh ſolicitude of him that ſhall be adorning his private Cabin when the Ship is ſinking. If neither the conſideration of the ſin of Schiſm, nor the diſhonour to our Religion, by our diviſions, will prevail to unite us, yet perhaps the apprehenſion of danger may. It was obſerved of old, that the Conqueſt of this Iſland by the</hi> Romans <hi>was facilitated by the inteſtine diviſions of the Inhabitants.</hi> Dum ſinguli pugnant univerſi vincuntur. <hi>And we have too great cauſe to fear the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious intereſts of this Nation now may be endangered upon the ſame point that the Civil were loſt then; I mean, that while we conteſt with one another, and with our Rulers about little things, we loſe the main, and by the opportunity of our diviſions and ſub-diviſions, a common Enemy break in upon us.</hi> — <hi>And therefore, unleſs we could be ſo fond as to perſuade our ſelves we have no Enemies; or ſo mad as to think them as ſupine as our ſelves, it muſt be unreaſonable preſumption to think our ſelves ſafe in this diſtracted condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now further to illuſtrate the dangerous principles of the Presbyterians, and other Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> let us conſider what King <hi>James</hi> in the Conference at <hi>Hampton Court</hi> did firſt declare. <hi>That of all the Tranſlations of the Bible into the</hi> Engliſh <hi>tongue, that of</hi> Geneva <hi>was the worſt, and that the Notes upon it were partial, untrue, ſeditious, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring too much of dangerous and tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erous conceits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> his Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on the Church-Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Brittain,</hi> pag. 178.</note> 
               <hi>his Majeſty inſtanced in two places, the one in</hi> Exod. 1.19. <hi>when diſobedience to Kings is allowed of. The other,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.16. <hi>Where</hi> Aſa <hi>is taxed for depoſing his Mother, and not killing her; a Note whereof</hi> (as the Author of the ſaid relation ſpeaks) <hi>the Scottiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians <hi>made ſpecial uſe of, not only depoſing</hi> Mary <hi>their lawful Queen, but perſecuting her openly and under hand, till they had taken away her life. Again, the</hi> Geneva <hi>notes upon</hi> Matth. 2.12. <hi>promiſe ought not to be kept, where Gods honour and preaching of his Truth is hindered, or elſe it ought not to be broken. Now what a wide gap</hi> (as the ſaid Author further obſerves) <hi>doth this open to the breach of all Promiſes, Oaths, Covenants, Contracts and Agreements; not only betwixt man and man, but between Kings and their Subjects; what Tumults, Rebellions have been raiſed in all parts of Chriſtendom, in</hi> England, Scotland, Ireland,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56020:5"/>France, <hi>the</hi> Netherlands, Germany, <hi>under colour that Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and the preaching of the Truth is hindered. If this once paſs for good Doctrine, neither the King, nor any of his good Subjects, in whatſoever Realm, can live in ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to dangerous practices, <hi>it is ſet out by</hi> Mr. <hi>James Howel</hi> in the Life of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13th. K. of <hi>France. There were thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Rebellions that King ſuppreſt; moſt, if not all by the</hi> Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Proteſtants <hi>of that Kingdom: They being Enemies within doors; were made uſe of by diſcontented Princes upon all occaſions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the 4th. luſtre of his ſaid book.</note> And to teſtifie what their principles were, the ſaid Hiſtorian further relates the ſpeech of the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> the Head and Leader of them all, to an Aſſembly of the chiefeſt of them: Saying, <hi>Gentlemen, I pray do not ye think that ſince our cauſe is conjoyned with that of God, but that I continue as ſtrong a zeal and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as ever towards it</hi> — <hi>Can we doubt but our defence, though ☞lawful, as being for Religion and liberty of Conſcience</hi> — <hi>For although our Parſons cry out daily in their Chairs, that we ought not to deſpair of Heavenly ſuccour, yet receiving every day proofs of the Wrath of the Eternal, there is more appearance to expect puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our ſins, than miracles for the re-eſtabliſhment of our affairs</hi> — <hi>If your wiſdoms find it to purpoſe that it be more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to ſeek our Conſervation with the exerciſe of our Religion and liberty of Conſciences within the obedience which we owe to our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince than in Reſiſtance; which though juſt in it ſelf, is held by the Enemies of our faith no other than Rebellion and High ☞Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which may be added the Teſtimony of the famous <hi>Grotius,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>If we inquire into the cauſes of the Wars which have ſo long waſted</hi> Europe, <hi>we ſhall find the flame to have been kindled principally by them that ſhould have been the Preachers of Peace. That the Civil Wars of</hi> France, <hi>moſt of them, were raiſed by them that ſtile themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel, needs no ſtronger witneſſes than the freſh memory of Kings, Peers, and People, together with very many Letters both of the Duke of</hi> Bouillon <hi>and</hi> Pleſſis <hi>complaining thereof: And alſo the very Comentaries which the Duke of</hi> Rohan <hi>hath written of the laſt Wars. Yet I except</hi> Camero, <hi>who was ever of another mind, and fared much the worſe for it; if there were any more like him, I would not deprive them of their due praiſe. We have ſeen a prodigious thing, Troops and Companies muſtered, Arms and Ammunition gathered under the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56020:5"/>name of the Reformed Churches: Whence is this power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> his Vote for the Churches Peace.</note> 
               <hi>from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or from Earth? For my part, being one who do not only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade Subjects from taking Arms, but intreat Kings alſo to make a ſparing uſe of their Prerogatives, who think them to be leſs miſerable that are Condemned to the Galleys, than ſuch as are devoted to an everlaſting War.</hi> And the ſaid Author in another place, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome dangerous opinions, ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Some opinions there be, that will not permit any State longer to be ſafe than force is wanting. Many think that there is every where a certain Contract or Covenant between God, the King, and the People upon ſuch terms; that if the King depart from God, the people alſo may deſert the King.</hi> And the ſaid Author inſtanceth in divers particulars. <hi>Thoſe firſt, as they imagin depart from God, that acknowledg the Popes primacy in the Church; for in all reaſon they muſt loſe that power which they have delivered up unto the Beaſt. Thoſe next, who attempt any Reconcilement with that Church that co-heres to the</hi> Roman Church, <hi>that is, with the ſynagogue of Satan, as they pleaſe to ſpeak. Laſtly, thoſe who retain any of the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ☜ uſed in the</hi> Roman Church, <hi>ſuch as are retained not in</hi> England <hi>only, but in the Northern Kingdoms, they are all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical, and therefore Idolatrous</hi>—And the ſame Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus, <hi>Theſe are in truth things ſomewhat ridiculous, but of a very ſad conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further ſpeaking of obedience to Governours— <hi>I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate into Subjects obedience towards them all according to the precept of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: Let them deſire the beſt, give God thanks for the middle ſort, bear with the worſt for the doctrin and example of Chriſt; let them ſuffer even crafty Foxes, ſuch as</hi> Herod, <hi>cruel Lyons, ſuch as</hi> Nero. <hi>And when I ſpeak of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, under that name I comprehend alſo inferiour Magiſtrates, ☜ who in reſpect of the higheſt power are but Subjects, ſent by the King as St.</hi> Peter <hi>ſaith: I preach not</hi> Evangelium armatum, <hi>an armed Goſpel</hi> — <hi>not Obedience only, but Honour alſo, and Reverence are due unto them, even to the froward; what elſe ſaith</hi> Sophocles, <hi>they are Princes:</hi> But St. <hi>Paul</hi> with Apoſtolical gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, <hi>They are Gods Miniſters: And if the doubtful actions, even of private men, are according to the rule of Charity to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the better part; how much more of Kings, who are not bound to render an account of their actions to any, nor can they ſomtimes do it without peril of the Common-wealth.</hi> Alſo as a worthy Divine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56020:6"/>heretofore of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſpeaking of the duty of Subjects, ſaith thus, <hi>We muſt look to our place, where God hath ſet us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> in Souls conflict.</note> 
               <hi>if we be in ſubjection to others, their Authority ought to ſway with us; neither is it the calling of thoſe that are Subjects to enquire over-curiouſly into the myſteries of Government, ☞for that both in Peace and War, breeds much diſturbance, and would trouble all deſigns.</hi> And the late Learned and Judicious Doctor <hi>Hamond</hi> delivers himſelf thus:<note place="margin">Practical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm.</note> 
               <hi>You may diſcern</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how far from the practice and Goſpel of Chriſt are thoſe doctrins of Ambitious men, which have made Chriſtian Religion a ground or excuſe of moving and diſquieting of States, and ſhaking, if not diſſolving of Kingdoms: All that will be uſeful to learn from thence,</hi> ſaith that worthy Author, <hi>is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtianneſs of thoſe actions in Subjects, which are built on ſuch Antichriſtian principles as theſe; ſuch are Rebellions, Treaſons, Sedition, attempting the Commotion of States on colour of Religion. I ſhall put you in ☞ mind of this great Truth, That Chriſt and his Diſciples were of all the Doctors that ever were in the world, the moſt careful to preſerve the doctrin and practice of Allegiance, even when Emperors were the greateſt oppoſers of the Chriſtian Religion: And if we mean to be accounted followers of them, we muſt go and do likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Primitive times</hi> (as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>believing was not an excuſe for diſobedience, or a commutation for a holy life, but a foundation of obedience to all the Laws of God and man; then all the profeſſors of Chriſtianity had one heart and one lip.</hi> Defendenda Religio eſt, non occidendo, ſed moriendo, non ſaevitia, ſed patientia, non ſcelere ſed fide, illa enim bonorum ſunt, haec malorum. <hi>Lactantius</hi> his Admonition. And further (as a late Author ſpeaks) <hi>It is by Gods ſpecial appointment and deſignation that Kings are his Vicegerents in the world: It is by his peculiar care and protection that their Authority is preſerved, and that their perſons are at any time fenced from the malicious deſigns, or the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious violences of wicked and unreaſonable men. The nature of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the world is ſuch, that it requires a divine wiſdom, and an uncontroulable power to ſuſtain it, and to maintain its intereſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſame purpoſe the worthy <hi>Grotius</hi> afore-mentioned ſpeaks, in his excellent diſcourſe of God and his Providence. <hi>That God permitteth not the effects of malice to range whither they would, but reſtrains them ſo, that Government might never be overthrown, nor the knowledg of divine Laws utterly extinguiſht.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56020:6"/>
            <p>And 'tis a known wiſe ſaying of <hi>Tacitus</hi> (as a late Author alſo hath it) Bonos Principes expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere debemus qualeſcunque pati; Et quomodo ſterilitatem, aut nimios imbres, &amp; caetera. naturae mala, ſic luxum &amp; avaritiam dominantium tolerare. <hi>The world muſt be governed as it may be, not by</hi> Angels, <hi>but by men</hi> — <hi>And there never was any lawful Magiſtrate ſo bad, whoſe Laws and Government were not more conducive to the preſervation of the common good, than his oppreſſion was to ſubver it. And 'tis wiſe to ſuffer a leſs evil, rather than loſe a greater good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now how dangerous and deſtructive the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and Phanatick Principles and Practices before mentioned are? How ſubverſive of all Government, Order, and Peace in the world? And how contrary to the Doctrin of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> I leave to all wiſe, ſober, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Chriſtians to conſider? more fit to be abominated and deteſted, and exploded out of the Chriſtian world, than cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and countenanced. What more miſchievous and wicked principles in the world than theſe two Antichriſtian Doctrins? Firſt, that nothing ought to be practiſed in and about the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, but what we muſt have an expreſs rule or warrant for out of the Scriptures. Secondly, that we may do wickedly, rebel againſt our lawful Prince, break our Oaths and Promiſes for the ſake of Religion. The firſt of which, at one ſtroak, cuts the throat of all Eccleſiaſtical Government, and thereby lays waſt the Church. The ſecond turns the world into a Shambles, brings in nothing but War, Blood, and Confuſion, and thereby lays waſt the State.</p>
            <p>And when we ſhall conſider, as Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> hath obſerved,<note place="margin">Of the Idolatry practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> p. <hi>372.</hi>
               </note> that the Jeſuits furniſhed the Enemies to Epiſcopacy, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with ſo many Arguments to their hands, to manage their bad cauſe with; this way of proceeding makes men wonder at them and ask the queſtion and ſay, What other reaſon can be imagined, why theſe men of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable and inſolent ſpirits and principles are now ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in proſecution of the Romaniſts, from the worſt of whom (<hi>viz.</hi> the Jeſuits) they take their principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; but only this, That certainly they are emulous of of having the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to have a hand in doing that, which as the cauſe of God, a noble and worthy atchievement, they are reſolved to do themſelves; that is to ſay, to ruinate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56020:7"/>the once famous and flouriſhing Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Bulwark of the Proteſtant Religion; being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved ſhe ſhall fall by no other hand but theirs, which in the end will aſſuredly prove no other than the reſolution of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> to pull that excellent Fabrick down to the ground, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they themſelves periſh alſo in the ruins thereof.</p>
            <p>As for all ſuch howſoever, who have been in integrity of their hearts formerly ingaged againſt their lawful Prince and Soveraign, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon Religious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences; that have ſince manifeſted their abhorrence of ſo great a Crime (<hi>Et nullus pudor eſt ad meliora tranſire</hi>) ſo they deſerve to be reſpected by all good Proteſtants: But as for ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Proteſtants (for I cannot call all Diſſenters from <hi>Rome,</hi> Proteſtants, for then <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and his Religiouſly mad Crew were ſuch, which I cannot agree to) I ſay therefore, as for ſuch pretended Proteſtants as ſhall ſtill perſiſt in their ſaid wicked and deſtructive principles and practices, and are ready once more to involve theſe Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> in War and Blood, upon the account of Religion: I ſhall ſay no more but this, <hi>Quos Jupiter vult perdere dementat prius.</hi> Let them beware, and that whenever they ſhall appear in action, as they will be then certainly doing the works of darkneſs, ſo the Prince of darkneſs will aſſuredly be their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, the innocent Blood of the Martyr'd <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed memory, will attend them, and the Lord of Hoſts will be againſt them, and the iſſue muſt needs be accordingly aſſured deſtruction; for <hi>Pertinaciae nullum remedium poſuit Deus.</hi> And they whoſe wickedneſſes are winked at for a time, are wont to pay dearly for the forbearance of their puniſhment, and muſt ſuffer what God ſhall command, becauſe what he commands they would not do, as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>Now dear Country men, <hi>Truth hath a Cognation with the ſoul</hi> (as one ſpeaks) <hi>ſo Lyes and Impoſtors are no more able to make reſiſtance againſt the power of Truth breaking forth, then darkneſs is able to diſpute with light.</hi> Yea, Truth is the Off-ſpring of God, and mother of Peace. Let us from the conſiderations aforeſaid be exhorted to abhor that which is evil, and cleave to that which is good: Let us weigh things well in the balance of reaſon; for ſhall it be ſaid of us <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> that we are the greated Fools or Mad-men in the world; that when Nature
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56020:7"/>hath by our ſituation made us as it were impregnable as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt forreign Enemies; that when they have not been able to hurt us; that we have deſtroyed our ſelves by our ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable and tumultuous tempers, by our Diſobediences, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, and Contempts of lawful Authority. Is not Order, Rule, and Government the ſinews of the Univerſe? Is it not that which upholds Kingdoms and Nations, yea, the whole world? And can there be any ſuch thing as Government without due, orderly, and peaceable ſubjection of Subjects to their Prince? the Prince to command according to his Laws, and his Subjects to obey. And doubtleſs the juſt Prerogatives of the Crown, and the Subjects Liberties are conſiſtent one with another; and when there is no incroachments made on either part, the Prince and People are very happy. <hi>Protectio trabit ſubjectionem, &amp; ſubjectio protectionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alaſs! are we not become Fools or Children in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and are not able to call to mind the actions of the other day? Cannot we call to mind the years Forty-one and Forty-two, with the mad and tumultuous proceedings of thoſe times, together with the ſad and doleful effects thereof, what then was the conſequence of the loud clamours againſt Popery and Prelacy, and of the ſeditious Petitionings, the factious ſupporting and countenancing of that Factious and Diſloyal Cabal, that Peſt and Plague of the Nation, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved us in War, Blood, and Confuſion, till at the laſt we had loſt our Religion Laws, and Liberties, and were reduced to a perfect condition of Slavery, to a company of Red-coats, a Mercenary Army, and in that ſad condition muſt have lain to eternity, had not the Almighty miraculouſly delivered us, by the happy Reſtoration of his Gracious Majeſty that now is. And can we now hate the effects, and yet be in love with the cauſe? And are we ſo void of reaſon, as not to conſider that now the ſame cauſes will (in all probability) produce the like, or as bad effects, eſpecially when there ſeems to be a Tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of ſouls, when the ſame ſouls now ſeem to animate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodies? Or rather that there are the like ill ſpirits raiſed and conjured up from the bottomleſs pit by ſome Diabolical and Schiſmatical Conjurers of our times, who make uſe of the names of God and Religion, as charms to that purpoſe. Are we not yet ſenſible that there are Juglers and Cheats in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56020:8"/>among us, that the <hi>piae fraudes</hi> are not only to be found at <hi>Rome? But I beſeech you conſider, that the power of Truth</hi> (as one ſpeaks) <hi>is victorious in ſober men, and will not ſuffer us to be cheated with falſe ſhews.</hi> Oh what Religious and glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences have been made uſe of in our late times of Confuſion, for the effecting the horrideſt and fouleſt facts? And can we be ſo ſenſeleſs not to perceive that there are ſome among us begin the ſame dance again, by clamoring againſt Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and proſecuting lately Petitions, and thereby (as it may be juſtly thought) counting their numbers as formerly? But let all true-hearted Proteſtants not fear their thouſands or ten thouſands, ſo long as they cannot make God of their number. And whereas to palliate, if not juſtifie the proceedings of thoſe times of Uſurpation, they would indeavour to make the King one of the three Eſtates. To ſay no more, they may find their vain fanfie and opinion diſowned even by <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in his Inſtitutes, who there maketh the Prince diſtinct from the three Eſtates.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, dear Country-men, to conſider, <hi>That true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine zeal</hi> (as one obſerves) <hi>is no Coribantick fury, but a calm and regular beat, guided and managed by light and prudence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways acknowledging a due ſubordination to that Authority, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, that is over us.</hi> And ſhall we be nevertheleſs ſo infatuated and tranſported by our paſſions and humours up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diſcovery of a late Popiſh Plot, as to be Seditious, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous, and Ungovernable, and not to be able to recover our reaſon again, and conſult ſoberly our own ſafety? and will we not be governed and ruled by our Prince and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? Shall we rather like a company of mad men, with flambeaux and fire-brands in our hands, ſet all on fire about us? And may not the Papiſts triumph at our follies, and ſay among themſelves, what unwiſe people are we to trouble our heads with Plots, and loſe our Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, when we need run none of theſe hazards, but only ſit ſtill and have a little patience, and the pretended Proteſtants in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will do our work for us; that is to ſay, ruin and deſtroy the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the chiefeſt ſtrength of the Proteſtant Religion; yea, they will ſooner effect it themſelves, than we can by all our plots and deſigns;<note place="margin">Mark iii.25.</note> 
               <hi>For a Houſe divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56020:8"/>
            <p>And how can the Phanatick party in reaſon reproach and hate the Papiſts for thoſe Crimes and Villanies, of which they are ſo groſly guilty themſelves? For did the Papiſts plot and deſign the deſtruction of the King and State by the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Plot? And did not the Presbyterian and the reſt of the Phanatick party alſo afterward, by Gun-powder and Guns, Swords, Piſtols, and Bullets, and a cruel and wicked Rebellion, not only deſign, but effect and accompliſh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the King and State? There was this only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, The Papiſts were always unproſperous and unſucceſsful in their wickedneſs; but the Phanaticks were moſt proſperous and ſucceſsful in theirs Now let all impartial and ſober men judge which of theſe two wicked Adverſaries is moſt to be feared and provided againſt, either the wicked Papiſt that hath been diſappointed in all attempts, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly ſucceſsful and fortunately wicked Phanatick; the firſt being not a fortieth part of the Nation; and the latter (it is much to be feared) bearing the ſame proportion in number to true Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>Mahumetans</hi> bears to the Chriſtians at this day in the world. The Plots alſo of the one, <hi>viz.</hi> the Papiſts, being fully diſcovered, and thereby prevented: But the deſigns and ſubtil Contrivances of the other (although in malice little inferior to that of the Papiſt) lying ſtill under ground undiſcovered, ſaving what was manifeſt by the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Rebellion laſt year. And further, they are leaſt under ſuſpition of any ſuch deſign of Subverting the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> being Enemies within doors, Pretended Proteſtants. It very nearly concerns us Proteſtants therefore, I humbly conceive, to have a great care, that in avoyding <hi>Scylla,</hi> we be not ſwallowed up in <hi>Charybdis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And one would think that the ſaid Phanaticks, although they are ſo zealouſly bent to the Rigorous proſecution of the Papiſts, upon the account of the late Plot, do not certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there was really any ſuch Plot, or that the Papiſts were carrying on ſuch grand deſigns againſt the Proteſtant Religion: For if they did, ſurely they would not take that as an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to plot miſchief alſo againſt the Proteſtant Intereſt, as the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presbyterians did laſt Summer; who upon diſcovering of the ſaid Popiſh Plot, moſt wickedly Murdered the Innocent,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56020:9"/>and after broke forth into open Rebellion: For could there be ſuch a Rebellion, and yet no Presbyterian Plot in <hi>Scotland?</hi> And did there not at the ſame time, a Party among us here in <hi>England,</hi> ſo ſympathiſe with them, as to make loud clamours againſt our worthy Biſhops, branding ſome of them as Popiſh, yet could not endure to have the <hi>Scots</hi> ſtyled Rebels, but would take their parts? And therefore may it not be thought that the ſaid Rebel <hi>Scots</hi> had many Presbyterian Friends in <hi>England?</hi> And were they not formerly like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> or rather like <hi>Samſons,</hi> Foxes, tyed together with fire-brands in their tayls? And in that poſture did they not ſet all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in ſuch a flame as could not in many years be quenched, which was as bad (if not worſe) as the Firing of <hi>London?</hi> And muſt the Papiſts be only guilty, and theſe innocent, when as great wickedneſs, and from as bad principles are acted by the one, as by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? As if the Phanaticks had a Diſpenſation from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to break his Laws, and that they might be at once both Saints and Devils. Oh horrible! And ſhall that abſurd and wicked Doctrin and Principle ſtill find entertainment in the world among Chriſtians, yea, among the Proteſtants; that we may do wickedly for Gods cauſe,<note place="margin">Rom. iil. 8.</note> that we may do evil that good may come; as if his honour might be advanced by our tranſgreſſion of his Laws? Do not theſe men miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch and blaſpheme the holy Chriſtian Religion, and make it reſemble the Religion of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> that tolerates the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and Murdering of their Princes; and that was born in Arms, and breaths nothing but Arms, and by Arms is propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated? And do not their tenents ſeem to be very much tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured with that wicked Hereſie? That <hi>Dominio fundatur in Gratia,</hi> that Princes and Magiſtrates loſe their dignity by great ſins, and no longer ought to be obeyed? But doubtleſs theſe cannot be the principles and practices of good men, good Chriſtians, how then can we give them that appellation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we will make our ſelves liable to that Curſe, for calling evil good? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.20. But ſay we what we will, theſe muſt be the Godly party; for let them do what they will, they are of the number of Gods elect and choſen people, and that they are ſure of, becauſe they apprehend that benefit by faith:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56020:9"/>Theſe in truth are ſad deluſions, and of the number of thoſe opinions, which although they are ridiculous, yet are of a very ſad conſequence, as the excellent <hi>Grotius</hi> hath obſerved. But I would not be miſ-underſtood: I ſpeak not this to diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage true Piety and Vertue, which I highly honour and reſpect; but nothing is more hateful to me (and I think to all good men) than <hi>Ahabs</hi> Faſts, when it was for the deſtruction of <hi>Naboth,</hi> for doubtleſs, <hi>Simulata ſanctitas eſt duplex iniquitas.</hi> They will nevertheleſs ſay of me, that I am of a bitter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting ſpirit, and cruel towards them: But I ſhall ſay this for my ſelf, Thoſe that have to do with ſtubborn and inveterate maladies, it is cruelty in ſuch to uſe <hi>Lenitives,</hi> and not <hi>Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives.</hi> To which I may further add (in the words, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member of <hi>Zuinglius</hi>) <hi>In aliis manſuetus ero, in blaſphemiis in Chriſtum non ità.</hi> I dare appeal to the Almighty, that I have no ill will againſt their perſons, but only their wicked prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. I think I could be willing to ſacrifice my Life to reſcue them all from their ſad deluſions, and my Nation from ruin. But however, let them go on to ſtyle themſelves the Godly party, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or what they pleaſe; this will prove moſt certain, That when this Church and Nation is brought to deſolation and deſtruction, they will be as innocent of procuring the ſame, as <hi>Nero</hi> was of the Firing of <hi>Rome,</hi> when he actually ſet it on fire. And what is more unjuſt than for ſingle acts of Murder and wickedneſs to be puniſhed with death, and the deſtruction of whole Nations to be gloryed in as an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Atchievement and a Righteous cauſe. But to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to perſuade us all, if it be poſſible, to Unity and Peace, I ſhall inſert a notable ſtory, I think it is related in Mr. <hi>Stows</hi> Chronicle, as followeth,</p>
            <p>That upon occaſion of a great Inundation and overflowing of the Country near the <hi>Severn,</hi> there was a little Hill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about by the waters, whither had reſorted for ſafety, many Beaſts of ſeveral kinds and ſeveral natures, as Horſes, Cows, Sheep, Foxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who being all incompaſſed with a common danger, laid aſide, or rather forgot their Antipathies, and abode there quietly together, not any one offering to prey upon, or moleſt the others and when the waters were gone, ſo parted in peace. May we not; dear Country-men, hence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56020:10"/>learn of Brutes? And ſhall we not by reaſon do what they did only by inſtinct, and out of apprehenſion of danger; that is to ſay, lay aſide our Prejudices, Paſſions, and Animoſities; in tendency to ſecure our ſelves from danger. I ſay again: If our diſaffected parties did really believe there were ſuch a horrid and deſtructive Plot, would they not follow the common dictates of reaſon, and ingeniouſly confeſs and ſay, Alas! we now ſee by experience that our ſad diviſions have incouraged our Enemies to Plot the ruin of all Proteſtants; but we will for peace and ſafety ſake, now lay aſide our Animoſities and ſtubborn wills, we will come to Church, Baptize our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, receive the Sacrament, and Conform in all things to our Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt as far as we can. Laws we know muſt not ſubmit to us, but we to them; we will do any thing that is required of us, if it be not as clearly and plainly forbidden by Gods Word, as our obedience is there clearly and fully enjoyned, we are willing to do almoſt any thing for the ſecuring the Proteſtant intereſt: We now ſee our Adverſaries are Vigilant and Induſtrious for to procure our deſtruction; but we will be as Vigilant and Induſtrious for our Union and Preſervation. But alas, all the noiſe of the horrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the late Plot, hath not awakened us to take one ſober and wiſe ſtop towards the ſecuring the Proteſtant Cauſe, but like men in the water ready to be drowned, who lay about them for life, being filled with the apprehenſions of danger, yet take not one wiſe ſtroak to ſwim or ſave their lives, but all their actions tend, to haſten their deſtruction and ruin. Juſt thus it is with us.</p>
            <p>It is true, there are a ſort of people that are mighty zealous for proſecuting Papiſts, the innocent as well as the nocent, and thereby to enrage and exaſperate them more againſt us. And will ſcarce ſuffer our wiſe Governours to take ſober and juſt meaſures in that grand Affair. But in the mean time take no thought for Union among Proteſtants, in which conſiſts principally our ſafety, which is juſt as if a Captain of a Ship being ingaged in a Sea Fight, who is very eager to aſſault and miſchief his Enemy, yet takes no care to ſuppreſs the Mutinies in his Ship, or to ſtop her Leaks; And who ſees not the ſpeedy fatal end of his Valour: It is Enemies within doors that by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56020:10"/>the univerſal ſuffrage of mankind are always accounted worſe than thoſe without, <hi>hino illae lachrymae!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may we not be fully convinced by experience of the ſad Conſequence of unſound and wicked Doctrines and Principles, eſpecially meeting with Men of active Spirits, which makes them induſtriouſly wicked: happy were it, if it might be ſaid of them, <hi>Operòſe nihil agunt,</hi> but of theſe men it muſt be truly ſaid, <hi>Operòſe multum mali agunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sibs,</hi> in his Sermon on <hi>Cant. 1.2.</hi>
               </note> But as a worthy Proteſtant Divine heretofore taught in our Church. <hi>If we deſire aſſurance of Chriſt's Love, get a chaſt Judgment, free from Error, Hereſie and Schiſm</hi> — <hi>Chriſt is wonderful jealous of our Judgments</hi> — <hi>Whoſoever is corrupt in Faith is corrupt in Obedience in that degree, evil Opinions breed evil Life.</hi> To which I may add that ſaying <hi>Animus ager ſemper errat,</hi> And <hi>Ex uno abſurdo dato, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur mille.</hi> Now although in other reſpects they may be accounted ſober men, yet it may be ſaid truly of them, <hi>Quid prodeſt vinum non bibere &amp; ira inebriari?</hi> And do not theſe men place the main, if not the all, of their Religion in endleſs ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſities about indifferent things, neglecting in the mean time the more weighty things of Chriſtianity? Is it not incorporated into the very Principles of theſe mens Piety and Religion, to be always murmuring and clamoring againſt Government and Governours both in Church and State, to be creating and raiſing jealouſies and fears in the hearts of the People againſt their Prince, to aggravate his perſonal failings, when there is any, to be dividing, ſeparating and rending the Church and State into pieces? And alas! to do thus wickedly is the way now adays to be accounted a godly Man, a good Chriſtian, a good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. And thoſe that are good and ſound Proteſtants, that love their Prince, make Conſcience of obſerving the good Laws, Orders and Conſtitutions of both Church and State, they are reputed and repreſented preſently as Papiſts, or popiſhly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Et ſi ſatis eſt accuſare, quis innocens?</hi> although by this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, how highly do they tacitely and by Conſequence, commend the Papiſts whom they ſo hate and perſecute. And except in our forſaking <hi>Rome,</hi> we will run along with them to <hi>Munſter,</hi> we muſt of neceſſity be all Papiſts, although they cannot but acknowledge, that <hi>in medio conſiſtit virtus.</hi> May it not therefore in reaſon be thought, that if it were poſſible to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56020:11"/>raiſe <hi>Cranmer, Ridley</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> and the reſt of the famous Martyrs out of their aſhes, and that they were converſant among us as heretofore, that aſſuredly they would be cried out on for Papiſts, by theſe pretended Proteſtants of our times, and as ſuch be put to a ſecond Perſecution and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom alſo, eſpecially if they ſhould take a Journy into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And what can this tend to in the end? Indeed as formerly; ſo ſtill, do theſe men conſult that wicked Rule or Maxim, <hi>Audacter columniare, ſemper aliquid haerebit.</hi> And here it may not I think be impertinent to mention a paſſage of the before mentioned Hiſtorian,<note place="margin">In the Life of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Mr. <hi>James Howel</hi> ſpeaking of a fearful Combuſtion and Revolt of <hi>Catalonia</hi> from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> occaſioned much by the preaching Friers and Monks, whence faith he. This Aphoriſm may be collected, <hi>That the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments being miſapplied do greateſt miſchief, and prove moſt dangerous, And as of the ſweeteſt Wines is made the ſharpeſt Vinegar, ſo Church men who by their holy Function, and white</hi> ☞ <hi>Robes of Innocence ſhould be the ſweeteſt of all Profeſſions, who ſhould breath nothing but Peace, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Allegeance and Love, if they miſapply their Talent, and abandon themſelves to the Spirit of Faction, they become the bittereſt enemies, the moſt corroding cankers, and worſt vipers in any Commonwealth, and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the Prince, in regard that they having the ſway over the Conſcience, which is the Rudder that ſteers the actions, words and thoughts of the rational Creature, they tranſport and ſnatch it away whither they will; making the Beaſt with many beads conceive according to the Colour of thoſe Rods they uſe to caſt before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us, I beſeech you, dear Country-men, call to mind former things and learn wiſdom. How hath this poor Nation ſuffered many times heretofore by our inteſtine broils, as the Records of former times will inform us, And will we not ſuffer the experience of theſe things to inſtruct us, are we reſolved not to conſider? Doth not Wiſdom and Prudence direct us not to look only at the ſurface or firſt appearance of things, but to view and conſider them in their true and natural Conſequences, according to that ſaying, <hi>Quicquid agas pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter agas &amp; reſpice finem?</hi> When we are in a Storm, is it time them to be murmuring and mutining againſt our Pilot? Have we any reaſon to ſuſpect his wiſdom or faithfulneſs?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56020:11"/>may we not in all reaſon preſume that he that is at the helm beſt underſtands the condition of his Ship both its courſe and working, and therefore beſt knows how to ſteer her? And can we be ſo maliciouſly abſurd as to imagin that our excellent Prince and Pilot hath not a very great and intenſe Care for the ſafety of that Veſſel in which he himſelf is embark'd? Will not <hi>Caeſar</hi> take ſpecial Care of the ſecurity of the Ship that carries <hi>Caeſar</hi> and all his fortunes, <hi>Caeſar</hi> and all his Subjects? Can it be otherwiſe, but that the intereſt of the King and his Subjects muſt be both one and the ſame? And for ever let them be accurſed, may I ſay, that go about to divide them. Is not the King and his Subjects as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Twins, that mourn or rejoice together? When did ever diffidence and diſtruſt, fears and jealouſies in Subjects of their Prince make them happy? Fears and jealouſies in the People muſt needs cauſe fears and jealouſies in their Prince, and his fears increaſe theirs, and ſo run round in this diabolical and diſmal circle without end to the ruin of both. And when was this Nation ever more happy than in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, when where was ſo great affection in her People towards her, and confidence in her good Government, that there was no place left for fears and jealouſies; although as Sir <hi>Robert Naunton</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Fragmenta Regalia, ſhe left more Debts unpaid taken upon the credit of her Privy Seals, than her Progenitors did or could have taken up in an hundred years before her. Yet</hi> (ſaith ☜ he) <hi>we are naturally prone to applaud the times behind us, and to vilifie the preſent. It is certain when her Parliaments met, they never did capitulate or prefer their private concerns to the publick,</hi> viz. <hi>the Queens neceſſities, but waited their times, and in the firſt place gave their ſupplies, and according to the exigency of her affairs, yet failed not at laſt to obtein what they deſired, ſo that the Queen and her Parliaments had ever the good fortune to depart in Love, and on reciprocal terms, although afterwards in her Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Reign that happineſs did not continue, by reaſon of ſome few popular diſcontented perſons, ſuch (as with the fellow that burnt the Temple at</hi> Epheſus) <hi>would be talked of, though for the doing of miſchief.</hi> Thus ſpeaks the ſaid Author. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs 'tis not a Conteſting but Compliance with the Prince that tends to the honour and happineſs of a Nation or People. If
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56020:12"/>there were (may I ſay) none other to give their Votes at Election of Parliament-men now in our times, then was in queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign; that is to ſay, none but good and ſound Proteſtants, who had a zeal for their Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then we might expect the ſame good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in that great and illuſtrious Aſſembly as She met with; but when there is ſo many men of deſperate ſeditious and Phanatick ſpirits, bitter Enemies to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that give their Voices at Elections, and uſe ſo many arts to put by Worthy men, I humbly conceive ſo great good can hardly be expected, with any conſtancy or continuance at leaſt. Now as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Nulla res vehementius Rempublicam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet, quam fides.</hi> So I may ſay, if there was but affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and confidence in our gracious Soveraign, and his wiſe Conduct: And it is a true ſaying, <hi>Qui diligit Legem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligit Regem:</hi> If we that are Subjects, would love and honour our Prince (as I am ſure we ought in duty to do) our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prince could not but caſt a favourable Aſpect upon his loving Subjects, and what could there then follow but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual interchanging of affections with each other; that bleſſed circulation of love and kindneſs, like the circulation of the blood in the natural body: And what bleſſed fruits and effects might we enjoy from this excellent Athletick and healthy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of our body politick? And there would be no fears and jealouſies of the meeting and Aſſembling of Parliaments, and no need of preſenting one Petition for their ſitting. But doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it is a leſſer evil not to meet, than to meet and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. And therefore dear Friends and Country-men, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks when Religion, Laws, Allegiance, our own Peace and Safety, calls aloud to this duty of Love, how can we withſtand it? Diſorder and Confuſion alſo is ſo great an evil, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the ſubſiſtence of the world, and happineſs of man-kind, and diſturbance and ſubverſion thereof ſo hateful to me upon any pretence whatſoever: That if I were ſatisfied that my Religion did enjoyn or allow of any ſuch doctrins and practices, I ſhould for that very cauſe forthwith renounce my Chriſtianity, it being impoſſible for ſuch a Religion to proceed from God.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56020:12"/>
            <p>Oh! How can I but pitty <hi>Caeſar?</hi> What a vaſt burden now lies upon his ſhoulders? He had need be an <hi>Atlas</hi> to ſuſtein it. How have we his Subjects, vile Wretches, taken a ſurfet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready of our peace and plenty, under his mild and gentle Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Have we had any cauſe juſtly to complain thereof? Have we not ſat under our own Vines, and eat the fruit of our own Fig trees in peace and ſafety? Hath not Religion and Property been ſecured to us? Whoſe Ox hath he taken? Whom of the meaneſt of his Subjects hath he oppreſſed or injured? And therefore what can hinder our happineſs, if we will our ſelves? And ſhall we ſuffer our own phanſies to raiſe chymera's and deluſions, fears and jealouſies, and then torment our ſelves with them? Will we be offended with our Gracious Prince, becauſe he is but a man? However (I am ſure) he is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> the common Father of his People. I beſeech you therefore (if it be but for ſhame) let us ſhew our ſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> and not to be of the Off-ſpring of curſed <hi>Cham.</hi> And if we apprehend any faults to happen in Government or Governours, are we competent Judges in the caſe? When as Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Origines Sacrae,</hi> That a falſehood may frequently ſeem truer to common un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings than truth it ſelf. And doubtleſs this is never more true, than in matters of Government. And if there be any fault in Governours, are we that are governed faultleſs our ſelves? And are not the miſcarriages of Governours very often ordered and diſpoſed by God as a ſcourge, procured by the ſins of the people (if our Bibles ſpeak true) and when that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall happen to us, it may (I think) in reaſon, very<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.1:</note> very much ſilence our complaints.</p>
            <p>If Proroguing of Parliaments be an offence to us, is that any new or ſtrange thing under the Sun? Hath it not been often done, even in tranquil and peaceable times, and by the wiſeſt of Princes? And although it muſt be acknowledged that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments are an excellent conſtitution, and of excellent uſe, when they are not tainted by Prejudices, Animoſities, and Faction, and do not degenerate from their right ends and uſe, may they not be reputed as the Phyſick to the body politick; and (if ſo made uſe of, and not as its conſtant food) be of great benefit and advantage to the Nation. And here I ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56020:13"/>inſert the words of one of the greateſt States-men that the world ever had; the Cardinal <hi>de Richelien,</hi> to the Aſſembly of the Notables in <hi>France,</hi> in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth; he ſpeaks thus, <hi>The Sick ſometimes dye by too many Remedies, as well as none at all. I am bound to tell you by the by, that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh this Nation or State in its firſt ſplendor, there's no need of many Ordinances, but real executions, few words and many deeds will teſtifie both the good intentions and judgments of them whereof ſhe is compoſed.</hi> But though Parliaments are an excellent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, are they not like other ſublunary things, ſubject to corruption and abuſe, and we know <hi>Optima vitiata ſunt peſſima.</hi> The beſt things when corrupted, prove the worſt, which I think our own experience hath not long ſince, taught us in Characters of blood: For if a General Council may err, can a Parliament be infallible. And what hath happened to that excellent Conſtitution, may it not happen again? But here by the by it may be obſerved, That it is not ſo much a Parliament ☞ is deſired by ſome among us, as ſuch a Parliament as might ſerve their deſigns; for thoſe very perſons, ſome of them that not long ſince were altogether for diſſolving of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>viz.</hi> that bleſſed healing Parliament firſt called after his Majeſties Reſtoration, are now the principal ſticklers for a Parliament.</p>
            <p>In the next place, if the decay of our Trade be an offence to us, may it not be juſtly thought that our own fears, our own diſtractions are the greateſt cauſe thereof: And then do we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be pityed, that ſuffer when we may cure our own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies? Let us confide and acquieſce in the wiſe conduct of our excellent Prince, and his wiſe Council, and be ſatisfied, and our Trade will return.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay? We in this Nation are a maſs of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, how miſerably divided in our minds, unanimous in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but in murmuring and complaining. Yet God who is truth it ſelf, is one, and unity, certainly is the fruit and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of verity. Now what a ſtrong Argument do we furniſh our Adverſaries the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> with againſt us, when they ſhall argue and ſay unto us, Where is that verity you ſo much boaſt of, when there is no unity but diſcord, ſtrife, and enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. And as St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks; <hi>If ye have bitter envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56020:13"/>and ſtrife in your hearts; glory not, and lie not againſt the truth; this wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, devilliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay? What mortal can pleaſe us? What mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Prince is able to govern us? How readily diſpoſed and bent are many among us, if it were poſſible, to be pulling down as formerly what is eſtabliſhed by Law? And yet alas! If ever God ſhould ſuffer ſuch a great and fearful judgment again to fall upon us, and that we ſhould be able to lay all things waſt as heretofore; will we not (as heretofore) be like the Builders of <hi>Babel,</hi> Confounded, although not in our language, yet in our different ends and deſigns, and never be able to agree what to eſtabliſh. I may further add, How is it poſſible for God Almighty himſelf to pleaſe that people, of whom ſome will have fair weather, and ſome foul, at one and the ſame time and place? Is it not juſt thus with us? What one faction or party would have, the other nauſeats and loaths. And what can our gracious Soveraign do with us; and yet what ſhowers of murmurings, clamours, bitter invectives and reproaches have our Governors ſuffered patiently? But let us conſider, God is not in the ſtorms, earth-quakes, and flames of murmuring and rebellious Subjects, but in the ſmall ſtill voice of humility and obedience: All Murmurers and Rebels are and ever were the Children of Pride; and we know God reſiſteth the proud, but vouchſafeth his grace and bleſſing only to the humble. How contrary are theſe things to our Allegiance to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord? Our Law ſaith, <hi>Ligeantia eſt vinculum fidei, lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antia eſt legis eſſentia</hi> It is the bond of our faithfulneſs, the very eſſence of the Law. And again, <hi>Ligeantia Domino Regi debita eſt Lex.</hi> It is the Law due to our Soveraign Lord the King.</p>
            <p>And it is worthy our obſervation, what hath uſually been the diſmal effects of Rebellion and defection from a lawful Prince. In that great defection of the ten Tribes from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> God did not vouchſafe them after it ſo much as one good King to govern them, they were all ſtark naught, and at laſt were carried away Captive, and totally deſtroyed, there remaining no memory of them at this day. Yea, to omit other inſtances, hath not our own late experience alſo taught us the ſame, after our wicked Rebellion againſt our lawful
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56020:14"/>Prince, and imbrewing our hands in his Innocent blood? How did God Plague us by our own diviſions and confuſions, and raiſed up a cruel Tyrant, <hi>Cromwel,</hi> to rule over us with a rod of Iron, and at once to cut the throat of our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, and made our very Nobles to ſtoop and lackquay ☞ after his Major Generals, and reduced us all into a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſlavery. And can we forget this ſad Calamity we ſo lately ſuffered?</p>
            <p>How hath he, whoſe Perſon and Authority ought to have been Sacred among us, ſuffered from his Subjects, not to be mentioned without abhorrence? Thoſe that are unfit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, yet will not be governed. So that I may ſay, what hath been ſpared to his Sacred Majeſty but his Cown? what bold daring Petitions of late promoted, and ſome preſented to his Royal Hand, contrary to his expreſs Royal will and pleaſure, which have ſignified no more but to let him know, that the Petitioners were diſſatisfied in his Majeſties Wiſdom and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity; that they better knew how to direct and guide State-affairs than himſelf. Have we not by our unworthy carriage towards him, as heretofore towards his Royal Father, given credit to that bitter Invective againſt our Nation, that <hi>Rex Angliae eſt Rex daemonum.</hi> Are we not aſhamed at theſe things, to be thus increaſing our Princes burden of Government, vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and torturing his Royal heart? How monſtrouſly abſurd are we herein? We all pretend to be very tender of his Majeſty, to be mightily concerned for his ſafety, and cry out <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> let the King live; and ſeem to be much incenſed againſt the Papiſts, becauſe in their late Plot they deſigned his deſtruction; and yet we are increaſing the burden he undergoes by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, murmurings, and complainings, our untractable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governable tempers; as if we had a mind to take the work and deſign of the Papiſts out of their hands; for can theſe horrid actions be the way to prolong his days? But it is my hopes, and I think I have reaſon to induce me to believe, that the late ſhakings of the Royal Oak, will cauſe it to take deeper root, and thereby ſtand the ſtronger.</p>
            <p>When I conſider the ſtate of things and perſons among us at preſent, I am ready to be filled with horrour, and cannot but deeply reſent his Sacred Majeſties condition, the only ſupport of my hopes is him, by whom Kings Reign: When I conſider
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56020:14"/>the innumerable train of Atheiſts, not only thoſe in practice, but the bold daring profeſſed Atheiſtical ſpirits, the ſmoak of the bottomleſs pit, the reproach of human nature: Who dare be ſo wickedly abſurd, as to contradict the univerſal ſenſe of all man-kind from the beginning of the world until this day, and ſay they were all fools but themſelves; who daily make it their ſport and paſtime to drol and jeſt at all Religion, blaſpheme and defie that God by whom they ſubſiſt, and Idolize and adore on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves, who own no other rule to walk by, but their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, their pleaſure, profit, and honour. Now what good Subjects theſe are like to prove, I leave to all wiſe and ſober perſons to conſider? He that only for his intereſt will be Loyal, when it is his intereſt and advantage will be a Rebel: He that defies and blaſphemes his God, can he honour and reſpect his Prince? Can he that is guilty of <hi>Dei-cidium</hi> be offended with <hi>Regis cidium,</hi> eſpecially when it ſhall be for his preſent ſecular advantage. <hi>Animus meminiſſe horret!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on the other hand, when I recollect the numerous Troops of Phanaticks and diſaffected of all ſorts, where a man may ſooner find (according to <hi>Samſons</hi> Riddle) hony in a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten carcaſe, than Loyalty to their Prince, further than what tends to advance the intereſt of their ſeveral parties; for accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Standard of the Covenant, they will be true and faithful to their Prince, but with this limitation and reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, In defence of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Liberties of the Subject: So that whenever they are diſpoſed to entertain fears and jealouſies of their lawful Soveraign, and cry out Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Tyranny; and take the confidence to ſay their Prince favours Papiſts, and intends to introduce an Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that party falſly and wickedly ſuggeſted againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed memory, then alas all their Loyalty paſſeth away as the morning dew.</p>
            <p>Where ſhall I after this ſearch, find good and loyal Subjects, that will ſtick to their Prince in time of need? Even all the good and ſound Proteſtants of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> even ſo many, and no more good Chriſtians may be reckoned true and loyal Subjects. For he that is a true Son of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a true Proteſtant, will ſay, be my Prince what he will (if God ſo pleaſe to permit it) ſo long as he is my lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, I dare not perjure my ſelf, and forſake my Allegiance; I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56020:15"/>muſt be juſt and loyal,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> I muſt give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due; I muſt ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice my life at his command, in his defence; I muſt not, I dare not reſiſt in any caſe, <hi>for they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation,</hi> Et mori non metuo ſed, damnari metuo. If a Prince hath a juſt and undoubted legal Title to a Crown by the Laws of God and Nature, and the Fundamental Conſtitutions of the Kingdom, I would willingly know by what Law he can be deprived thereof? For can any power on Earth nullifie or make void the Laws of God, and make that juſt which God Almighty, the great Law-giver hath made unjuſt. Is it not one of the maxims of our Laws of <hi>England,</hi> That where contrary Laws come in queſtion, mans Laws muſt give place to Gods Laws. And further, how far our Oaths of Allegiance bind us to our Prince and his Heirs, and lawful Succeſſors, we are to be informed thereof by our Prince, and preſent Governor, and his Council. For as the excellent <hi>Grotius</hi> ſpeaks concerning the force and obligation of an Oath, whereby Subjects are obliged to the Magiſtrates, <hi>I conceive</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Interpretation belongs to States-men and Lawyers, not to Divines.</hi> This is unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true, we muſt not do or conſent to any ſinful act to ſave our ſelves from the greateſt ſufferings; and I would have any one to ſhew me any piece of Chriſtianity to juſtifie me in doing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. If I were ſure that the next lawful and undoubted Heir to my preſent Prince and Governour were of another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, differing from mine; and knew certainly that he would perſecute me, nay burn me for an Heretick, I am bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nevertheleſs, and muſt of neceſſity own and be faithful to his intereſt and juſt right; for to be diſloyal, unjuſt, to perjure my ſelf knowingly, and with deliberation, would be aſſured damnation to me: But to run the utmoſt hazard, to keep a good Conſcience, and to ſuffer Perſecution, to loſe my life for the beſt Religion in the world (for ſuch mine muſt be to me) would be the greateſt comfort, happineſs, and glory that I am capable of in this life.</p>
            <p>May I now alſo wiſh all health and happineſs to that great and populous City of <hi>London,</hi> of which I am an unworthy Member; and may I humbly repreſent theſe few things to her worthy Citizens, their ſerious conſideration, That they would not be forgetful of thoſe late heavy Divine Viſitations, the dreadful Peſtilence; and more eſpecially that horrid Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56020:15"/>in which, whatever hands of men were inſtrumental, doubtleſs there was much of Gods hand: For that hand needs muſt be directed by more than an ordinary Providence, that ſhall with a pair of Dice throw Siz-Cinque a hundred times to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. May I alſo preſent before them, that <hi>nunquam proſpere ſuccedunt res humanae ubi negliguntur Divinae:</hi> As alſo what a Heathen obſerved,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Sic prophanatis ſacris,</l>
               <l>Peritura Troja perdidit primum Deos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They loſt their Gods before they loſt their City <hi>Troy.</hi> And if Heathens eſteemed it an Infamy not to be pious, what a ſhame will it be if Chriſtians think not ſo alſo. Next therefore to their piety towards God, may I recommend that which is inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to it, Loyalty to their Prince; as alſo the preſervation of the order and good Government of their City, under that prudent and worthy Perſon that now Governs them; in all which undoubtedly conſiſts their ſafety, ſplendor, &amp; proſperity. And that as they are very vigilant to prevent Firing their Houſes, ſo more eſpecially that they would have a care of ſuch wicked perſons, as by falſe rumors of firing of Houſes, and the like, drive on (it is much to be feared) a deſign to fill the peoples minds with fears and diſcontent, thereby to inflame them into Sedition and Rebellion; which if it ſhould ever take effect, might prove the dreadfuleſt and moſt fatal fire that ever befel that City. I make no doubt of the care therefore of all thoſe that are concerned in her preſervation, as to prevent burning of their Houſes, ſo more eſpecially of ſuch miſguided Zealots that diſdain ſuch pedling wickedneſs of ſetting ſingle Houſes on fire; but are moſt intently bent to the firing of whole Kingdoms, and that with the greateſt vigour and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry poſſible, as the cauſe of God, and advancement of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and of the Kingdom and Scepter of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, to bind their King in Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron; and dare be ſo ridiculouſly impudent to keep Faſts, and then beg of God to proſper the tranſgreſſion of his Laws. And alas! how many thouſands of theſe Fire-balls are to be found both in City and Country, and very little conſideration had of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of them; although by the experience of the whole world,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56020:16"/>they have been ever found fatal to the Citys and Countrys where they have proſpered and prevailed. And therefore it hath been ſaid truly, That ſome mens Prophaneſs and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries may be with leſs danger tolerated by the Magiſtrate, than ſome mens Religion, the very principles whereof are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ſubvertive of all Government, Order, and Peace. And thoſe Subjects who will not be ſatisfied without a general to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of all Religions (although it hath been found by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that ſuch perſons will not give (when they have power) that to others which they now crave.) If their Prince and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour comply with their deſires, I humbly conceive it will oblige him to have a good ſtanding Army to keep them at peace among themſelves; and to ſupport his Government, and preſerve himſelf in ſafety; for every Sectary will take the Bible into his hand, and as readily will interpret it, as read it, and ſay, here is the Infallible rule, and I have the ſpirit to interpret it: And the conſequence is, They make their own fancies and conceits as the Oracles of God, either in oppoſition one towards another, or againſt their lawful Prince and Governour. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to this purpoſe the worthy <hi>Grotius</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Some Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſay, they are led by the publick authority of the ſpirit, in his word common to all Chriſtians.</hi> As much was ſaid by <hi>Socinus, Brown,</hi> and ſo many others. <hi>See into what perplexities the hearers minds are on every ſide involved. Here (ſaith every Sect) is the Word of God pure and ſincere, according to the ſenſe of the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: They know not whither to turn themſelves, but muſt abide there where their Birth or Education, or hope of profie and preferment hath placed them, and applaud their own men, ſpeaking loud and confident: Could any one free men out of this Labyrinth, were it not a happy work, and worthy of all acceptation?</hi> Which queſtion he elſewhere reſolves thus, <hi>Conſuetudo veterum Chriſtianorum eſt optima Scripturarum interpres.</hi> The cuſtom or practice of the Antient Chriſtians is the beſt Interpreter of the Scriptures. For as the ſaid Author further adds, <hi>Thoſe Primitive Chriſtians beſt underſtood the ſenſe and meaning of the Scriptures, and did beſt practice the Chriſtian Doctrin contained in the Scriptures.</hi> For doubtleſs, if we will ſearch for the Chriſtian verity in its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt luſtre and purity, we muſt have recourſe to the pureſt ſtreams flowing neareſt to the fountain, even the Primitive times. But how can we but groſly miſtake, if we will wreſt the Sacred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56020:16"/>Scriptures, and expreſly in contradiction to St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2.17. apply the promiſes of the ſpirits guidance to our times, which were intended for thoſe firſt times of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude my diſcourſe with an excellent and wiſe caution given to Proteſtants by a Learned Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Cudworth <hi>his Sermon at</hi> Lincoln-Inn, 1664.</note> which deſerves to be imprinted upon all our minds that wiſh well to the Proteſtant intereſt. <hi>That unleſs there be a due and timely regard had to the commands of lawful Authority in indifferent things, and to order, peace, and unity in the Church. It may be eaſily foreſeen that the Reformed part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom will at length be brought firſt to Confuſion by crumbling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to infinite ſects and diviſions, and then to utter ruin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now dear Country-men, what can I do more, but bewail and lament our follies, abſurdities, and confuſions? Oh! how great need have we of an <hi>Amphion</hi> with his Lute, with his Charming melody to mollifie and ſoften our rugged and ſtony hearts: Or rather of the great <hi>Hermoſtes</hi> (as the aforeſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor calls him) that tunes the whole world, to put us in tune, to reduce us to the uſe of our reaſon again, and cauſe us to live together in unity and peace? Oh that we were wiſe, that we would conſider; and that we might know in this our day the things belonging to our peace, and that they might not be hid from our eyes. And let it be all our Prayers, that we may be freed from all Pride, Error, Prejudice, and Partiality, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and obey the truth, that at the great day of reckoning, when we ſhall all be called to give an account of our deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this weak and imperfect ſtate, we all may be found not in the number of them who have deſpiſed Dominions, ſpeak evil of Dignities. But of thoſe whoſe lives have been anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the holy Chriſtian Religion, which is pure and peaceable.</p>
            <p>That which once moved <hi>Croeſus</hi> his dumb Son to ſpeak, when his Enemies were about to kill him (my affection to my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Prince, and Country) hath extorted from me this mean and unworthy Eſſay in tendency to quench thoſe flames I fear are breaking forth among us. And let us beware, and be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, for if we perſiſt in our wickedneſs, the very ſtones in our Streets ſhortly will (it is to be feared) cry out in judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, to our confuſion and deſtruction. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From all thy wrath, and from all our ſins, Good Lord deliver us.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
